Josef van Niekerk

7 Goffers House, Duke Humphrey Road, London, SE3 OTT

Phone: 078 5303 8174

Email: josef.jobsearch@gmail.com



SUMMARY

A decade's worth of experience as a software development, data analysis & relationship management professional in the financial services industry. Over 5 years' programming, project management, system design & management experience as well as more than 8 years' analytics & business intelligence experience, including building complex SQL queries, reporting suites and data migration routines.

I am passionate about solving problems and making improvements in any environment, and have a track record of doing this successfully, acquiring new information and expanding my skillset when required.

SKILLS

Languages

- Proficient in: PHP (5/7) with Laravel (7) & WordPress, Microsoft Visual Basic .Net, JavaScript (ES06),
 jQuery & Vue.js (v2 with Vue Router & VueX), SQL, MS Visual Basic for Applications (VBA), HTML5, CSS3
- Familiar with: C# .Net, C++, Python

Software

- Frameworks: Laravel, Vue.js, Bulma, Element.io, Bootstrap
- Platforms: Microsoft Windows 10, Vagrant, Docker, Linux, Git, AWS, Jira, Bitbucket, GitHub, HubSpot,
 Yotpo, Microsoft PowerBI
- Methodologies: SCRUM, Agile, Dependency Injection, OOP, Model-View-Controller (MVC), SOLID
- Database: Microsoft SQL Server & T-SQL, Microsoft Access, MySQL (5.7/8)

EXPERIENCE

Developer

April 2018 - April 2020

Uncle Buck Finance LLP

- Member of project team responsible for consulting with stakeholders to draw up specifications for required software functionality, system design & subsequent requirement and software development work. The team uses the SCRUM methodology to plan and execute projects using Jira stories.
- Designing & building the user interface for a new CRM the company is building in-house using Vue.js,
 Vue Router & VueX for a Single Page Application (SPA). Using JavaScript & CSS frameworks including
 Bootstrap, Bulma & Element.io for layout & templating.
- Playing a leading role in the design & implementation of the new CRM backend system, business logic & database using PHP with Laravel & MySQL.
- Designed & derived new CRM loan calculations logic & formulas, including standard loan contract & payment plan logic & calculations.

- Designed and built a new version of an integration between the company automated dialler system & the new CRM using PHP with Laravel & MySQL. Built the version for the current CRM using Visual Basic .Net & SQL Server while in my previous position of Analytics & BI manager.
- Helped design & implement the current technology suite for developers & testers utilising Docker for system setup & Bitbucket for version control.
- Created functionality in the existing customer portal on the company WordPress website to improve
 customer interaction with the company. This includes creating functionality to comply with EU & UK
 legal requirements such as building automated processes to give customers access to their data via Data
 Subject Access Requests (DSAR) & Statements of Accounts.
- Designed & created new bespoke pages on the company WordPress website to improve the call centre staff & underwriters' processes by giving them access to additional data & functionality not available in the current CRM. Used WordPress PHP & JavaScript, including jQuery to build page functionality & logic.
- Built automated document reader functionality to automate validation & processing of documents submitted by customers, e.g. payslips, using Amazon Web Services (AWS) Textract with Single Sign-On (SSO), the AWS PHP SDK & AWS CLI.
- 5+ years of building and maintaining VB.Net applications during both my roles at Uncle Buck Finance.

Analytics & Business Intelligence Manager

March 2014 - April 2018

Uncle Buck Finance LLP

- Built and managed the Analytics & Business Intelligence team for over 4 years.
- Performed analysis of a large SQL Server database for the company CRM and reported relevant results to various stakeholders within the company.
- Designed, built and maintained the company reporting suite using Microsoft PowerBI and bespoke macro enabled spreadsheets using Microsoft Excel with Visual Basic for Applications (VBA).
- Designed & built several SQL Server processes using complex SQL queries & procedures to compensate for the shortcomings of the current company CRM & improve business efficiency.
- Designed, built, project managed & maintained a complete integration between the external automated
 call centre dialler system & the company CRM. This included designing and building an MS SQL Server
 database for the integration platform to handle the relevant data in a staging environment and an MS
 .Net application with user interface to manage the integration process and API communication with the
 dialler provider to update data in dialler lists and download & process call attempts and outcomes in
 real time using Microsoft Visual Basic.
- Created and maintained automated daily Credit Reference Agency (Trans Union formerly Call Credit) data sharing reciprocity process using Microsoft SQL Server on SSMS and SSIS.
- Created the data migration processes to transfer data from the current CRM on SQL Server to a new system being built in-house using MySQL. Collation and migration processes built using T-SQL & MySQL.
- Created and maintained automated processes to improve system and loan book performance, including processes such as lead buying strategies and alerting using T-SQL on MS SQL Server.
- Built and maintained several VB .Net applications for various parts of the business to help optimise business processes and give stakeholders access to required data not directly available via the CRM UI.
- Created processes to prepare, email and store statutory notices using MS SQL Server.

Project managed data integration between CRM & website with HubSpot marketing suite.

Director & Treasurer March 2014 – June 2017

BCCA Trade Association (merged with CFA recently – cfa-uk.co.uk)

- As a director and board member, I was part of the team ensuring the continued success of the
 organisation in terms of financial viability and providing the services required by the members.
- Administered the financial assets and liabilities of the organisation.

Analytics & Lender Relations Manager

Feb 2012 - Feb 2014

Money Gap Group (formerly PDBUK)

- Built and managed the Analytics team and managed the relationship management team.
- Significantly improved company client relationships & turnover by designing, formalising and managing the company analysis, lender relationships and business development strategies and procedures.
- Designed, built and maintained reports used for the management of client accounts valued at over £2 million per month and for reporting to senior management and the accounts department.
- Analysis of client behavioural data using T-SQL on MS SQL Server, advanced MS Excel lookup & nested functions, pivot tables & VBA to improve business strategies.
- Collaborated closely with other departments to improve analysis processes, reporting and general operations, especially with CTO and the development team.
- Helped grow the company turnover by over 100% by analysing data and making strategic recommendations to management and clients, e.g. optimising lead buying strategies based on volumes & price points.
- Promoted twice during my time at the company.

Sales Executive Jan 2011 – Feb 2012

Pay360 by Capita (formerly PayPoint.net)

- Analysed business models and financials to assess suitability to the ecommerce market from the perspective of taking online card payments.
- Advised business owners and directors on appropriate business models to fit with banking and card scheme requirements and regulations.
- Negotiated settlement and other terms with underwriters on behalf of clients.

EDUCATION

University of York

York, United Kingdom

• Master's degree in Mathematical Finance (merit) – graduated in 2012

University of South Africa

Pretoria, South Africa

 Bachelors of Commerce degree with double majors in Operations Research and Business Management (with distinction) – graduated in 2009